<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-10-28T20:35:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Natalie’s Little Theorems</title><subtitle>A tech blog with a math twist!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Technology and Education</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/27/techeducation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology and Education" /><published>2018-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/27/techeducation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/27/techeducation.html">&lt;h1&gt;Technology and Education&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;post-meta&quot;&gt;Posted: Oct 27, 2018&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;i&gt;A greater focus on computer science in K-12 schools will lead to increased diversity in computer science and other related fields&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proof:
I can still clearly remember my first day of computer science class in college. I had not programmed prior to this class, but I entered with a cautious optimism as I knew I tended to do well with math and logic. But then the class began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My peers started raising their hands confidently asking about if we would be using Java or Python, and told stories of how they coded their calculators in middle school math. I realized that I had falsely assumed that most of the students in this &lt;i&gt;introductory&lt;/i&gt; class would be beginners like me. I felt such envy that many of them were able to take AP computer science in high school. If only I had been given that chance, maybe I would not have to work twice as hard just to catch up? Only after a few weeks in the course, I found myself wanting to give up. But as the saying goes, my mama did not raise a quitter. So I fought through it and found out, once I got over the learning curve, that I was pretty good at computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today, and I am still thinking about the series of events in ones life that may lead them to sit down in a computer science college class, try an online coding course, or sign up for one of the many bootcamps offered these days. While it is quite obvious that the computer science field today is composed of mostly white males, it is less obvious how we can change that. I believe that programming will remain a niche field only pursued by a mostly privileged group of students and professionals unless we integrate computer science into the K-12 curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By exposing younger children to programming you can prevent them from inheriting the negative stigmas often associated with computer science. When television shows and movies portray tech clubs or hackers, they tend to paint an unattractive picture of “geeky” people (mostly men) with an unhealthy obsession for technology. Why not show children that computers and technology are for everyone? Allow their interest to develop before they build unhealthy and untrue biases. I think this point is especially relevant for solving the gender gap, but it’s best that I save my thoughts on that for another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting point is that some students may not have the resources to explore technology on their own. It is wrong to assume that every child is growing up with technology at their fingertips these days. A recent &lt;a class=&quot;link-inside-post&quot; href=&quot;http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/10/26/nearly-one-in-five-teens-cant-always-finish-their-homework-because-of-the-digital-divide/&quot;&gt;study by Pew Research &lt;/a&gt; showed that 25% of lower-income teenagers do not have access to a computer at home. If public schools fail to offer computer science classes, these students without computers have little to no chance of stumbling into the field on their own even if the interest is there. The great thing about computer science is that you don’t need a computer to learn the foundational concepts. So even for schools that cannot afford laptops for every student, a valuable computer science course is still achievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About one year ago, Delaware’s Governor John Carney signed &lt;a class=&quot;link-inside-post&quot; href=&quot;http://legis.delaware.gov/BillDetail?LegislationId=25346&quot;&gt;a bill&lt;/a&gt; which requires public high schools in the state to offer at least one computer science course by the 2020 school year. While we may be years away from conducting real studies which can confirm the long-term effects of bills such as this one, we can enjoy observing the start of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that adding a computer science class to public schools is not the complete solution, but it is a step in the right direction. The diversity problem in technology is not going to fix itself, and now is the time to start making changes. You hear everywhere that “technology is the future”. If this is true, then isn’t it better to let everyone have the opportunity to build our tomorrow? QED.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Technology and Education Posted: Oct 27, 2018 A greater focus on computer science in K-12 schools will lead to increased diversity in computer science and other related fields</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/26/firstpost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2018-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/26/firstpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/26/firstpost.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;welcome&quot;&gt;Welcome&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello world&lt;/strong&gt;, this is my first Jekyll blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you like it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Welcome</summary></entry></feed>